<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    
    <properties>
        <title>
            Sample-Cluster Monitoring
        </title>
    </properties>
    
    <head>
        <meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=iso-8859-1"/>
        <link href="css/bam-docs.css" rel="stylesheet"/>
        <link href="styles/dist-docs.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" media="all"/>
    </head>
    <body xml:lang="en">
                
        <h1>
           Cluster Monitoring
        </h1>
        
        <p>
           This sample explains how a cluster of servers can be monitored and can obtain the useful analysis out of the collected data. This sample concentrates on the statistical analysis of a clustered environment. Throughout the sample we'll assume a clustered system as follows;
        </p>

	<p>
There are two data centeres and each having two clusters; One is a ESB(Enterprise Service Bus) cluster and other one is the AS (Application Server) cluster.For the this kind of  situation WSO2 BAM can be configured in such a way the request count, response count, etc for each cluster can be monitored. The below given diagram explains the architecture how WSO2 BAM can be connected the cluster in the above scenario.

	</p>
	<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_setup.png" alt="Cluster Monitoring sample setup" title="Cluster Monitoring sample setup"/></p>
	
	<p>As shown in the above diagram, the statistics from the each cluster is pushed in WSO2 BAM and the data is directly stored in the Cassendra data store. Analyzers can be written in order to process the gathered data by WSO2 BAM. The result of analyzers will be summarized and stored back in the cassendra data store. The summarized data can be presented in the gadget dashboard according to his/her requirement by using the Gadget-Ide in the WSO2 BAM.</p>

<p>Each of the above steps will be described in detail in the following steps. </p>


<h2>Step 1 - Start BAM Server</h2> 
<ol>
<li>Download the WSO2-BAM Server</li>
<li>Unzip the WSO2-BAM.zip in the location where ever you prefer</li>
<li>Go to WSO2-BAM-HOME/bin folder in comman prompt. And type</li>

<ul>
<li> wso2server.sh (For ubuntu, linux, mac OS)</li>
<li> wso2server.bat (For Windows)</li>
</ul>

</ol>
<br/>
<br/>

<h2>Step 2 - Sending events to BAM server from clusters</h2>
<p><b>Pre-requisites: Apache-ant</b> </p>
<p>Make sure you machine has apache-ant, if not please install the apache-ant.(http://ant.apache.org/) </p>

<ol>
<li>Go to location from command prompt WSO2-BAM-HOME/samples/cluster-monitor</li>
<li>In this folder you can see the build.xml. Type 'ant' command from the command propmt. This will simultate the data center siutation as showed in the figure and will pump the events to BAM </li>
</ol>


<p>The incoming data from the cluster to BAM will be as below;</p>
<p>
<pre>&quot;dataCenter&quot; : &quot;&quot;,
   &quot;cluster&quot; : &quot;&quot;,
   &quot;request_count&quot; : &quot;3&quot;,
   &quot;response_count&quot; : &quot;2&quot;,
   &quot;fault_count&quot; : &quot;1&quot;,
   &quot;response_time&quot; : &quot;3.5&quot;,
   &quot;clusterStream&quot; : &quot;cluster&quot;,
   ....}
</pre>
</p>
<br/>
<br/>


<h2>Step 3 - Create Index (ClusterStreamSelector)</h2>

<p>According to this situation we need to create two indexes.</p>
<ul>
<li>ClusterStreamSelector: For filter out the cluster stream data from huge amount of data stream stored in the cassendra data store</li>
<li>ClusterIndex: This index is needed to query the summarized data which is generated  by the analyzer</li>
</ul>

<p>At this moment we need to create the ClusterStreamSelector. Follow the below given steps to create the index.</p>
<ol>
<li>Login to the BAM management console. The link for the management console will be there in the server startup log. You can click on it and log in to the management console. Or you can  go to https://localhost:9443/ in your web browser, this will take you to the management console.</li>
<li>Go to Configure &#8594; Connection Parameters. There you can provide the connection parameter for the cassendra source. Default username, password is admin, admin. Click on Save button after filling out the connection paramters.</li>
<li>Go to Configure &#8594; BAM Database</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step1.png" alt="Add index main page" title="Add Index main page"/></p><br/><br/>

<li>Click on the Add Index.</li><br/>
<li>Create Index named ClusterStreamSelector, which filters out the clusterStream, as shown below. And click Save.</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step2.png" alt="Add Index" title="Add Index"/></p><br/>
</ol>
<br/>
<br/>

<h2>Step 4 - Create Analyzer</h2>
In the analyzer you need to write the analytics such that it analyzes the gathered data by the BAM according to you requirement. In this sample we are concerned about the request count, response count, fault count and response time of each cluster. Therefore the analyzer sequence for this requirement will be,

<p><pre>
&lt;analyzerSequence name="ClusterSummarizer"&gt;
    &lt;trigger cron="1 * * * * ? *"/&gt;
    &lt;analyzers&gt;
        &lt;get name="BASE" batchSize="1000"&gt;
           &lt;where index="ClusterStreamSelector"&gt;                                                                         
             &lt;range column="clusterStream" start="" end=""/&gt;
           &lt;/where&gt;
        &lt;/get&gt; 
        &lt;groupBy&gt;
            &lt;field name='dataCenter'/&gt;
            &lt;field name='cluster'/&gt;
        &lt;/groupBy&gt;
        &lt;drop type="column"&gt;
            &lt;fieldSet&gt;
                &lt;field name="correlationKey1"/&gt;
                &lt;field name="metaKey1"/&gt;
                &lt;field name="timestamp"/&gt;
                &lt;field name="ClusterStream"/&gt;
                &lt;field name="timeStamp"/&gt;
            &lt;/fieldSet&gt;
        &lt;/drop&gt;
        &lt;aggregate&gt;
            &lt;measure name="request_count" aggregationType="SUM"/&gt;
            &lt;measure name="response_count" aggregationType="SUM"/&gt;
            &lt;measure name="fault_count" aggregationType="SUM"/&gt;
            &lt;measure name="response_time" aggregationType="AVG"/&gt;
        &lt;/aggregate&gt;
        &lt;put name="clusterSummary" dataSourceType="CASSANDRA"&gt;
            &lt;onExist&gt;
                &lt;aggregate&gt;
                    &lt;measure name="request_count" aggregationType="SUM"/&gt;
                    &lt;measure name="response_count" aggregationType="SUM"/&gt;
            	    &lt;measure name="fault_count" aggregationType="SUM"/&gt;
                    &lt;measure name="response_time" aggregationType="AVG"/&gt;
                &lt;/aggregate&gt;
            &lt;/onExist&gt;
        &lt;/put&gt;
        &lt;get name="clusterSummary"/&gt;
        &lt;log/&gt;
    &lt;/analyzers&gt;
&lt;/analyzerSequence&gt;
</pre></p>

<p>The above given analyzer sequence is given in the WSO2BAM/Samples/cluster-monitor/ClusterSummarizer.xml. Follow the below given steps to ad dthe analyzer sequence to the BAM server.</p>

<ol>
<li>Go to WSO2BAM/samples/cluster-monitor folder</li>
<li>Open the ClusterSummarixer.xml and copy the content</li>
<li>Go to Configure &#8594; Analyzer Framework</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step3.png" alt="Add analyzer main page" title="Add analyzer main page"/></p><br/><br/>
<li>Click on 'Add sequence' and go to the source view of the analyzer sequence.</li><br/><br/>
<li>Paste the content from the ClusterSummarizer.xml in the step-2, and click on 'Save All' button.</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step4.png" alt="Add analyzer" title="Add Analyzer"/></p><br/><br/>
</ol>

<p>After adding the summarizer, you can see the below summarized data in the server log.</p><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step5.png" alt="Summarized server log" title="Summarized server log"/></p><br/>
<br/>
<br/>

<h2>Step 5 - Create Index (ClusterIndex)</h2>
<p>This index is used to query the summarized data and create the gadget using that. This is similar to the step 3 where we created the ClusterStreamSelector. </p>

<ol>
<li>Go to Configure &#8594; BAM Database</li>
<li>Click on Add Index</li>
<li>Create the index as in the below figure. Click on the 'Add column' to add the second column field.</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step6.png" alt="Create Index - ClusterIndex" title="Create Index - ClusterIndex"/></p><br/><br/>
</ol>

<p>Now you can see two index from the index table as below.</p><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step7.png" alt="All Index table" title="Table of created Indexes"/></p><br/><br/>


<h2>Step 6 - Create Gadget</h2>
<p>In this section we cna see how to design your own gadgets according to your requirement. In this section we created bar chart, pie chart and table to visulaize the data created by BAM.</p>

<p>The below given steps will explain how to create the gadgets and visualize the data collected from the clusters of servers.</p>

<ol>
<li>Go to Configure &#8594; Gadget IDE</li>
<li>In order to obtain the unique data center names, there is a web service in BAM. To communicate with web service, click on the 'Web Service (WSDL)' in the Gadget IDE.</li><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step8.png" alt="Web sevice gadget" title="Web service gadget"/></p><br/><br/>

<li>You can see the WSDL of the web service mentioned above, in https://localhost:9443/services/IndexAdminService?wsdl2. Insert this WSDL file url in the gadget, as below. And click on 'load' button.</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step9.png" alt="Web service gadget after load" title="Web service gadget after load button pressed"/></p><br/><br/>

<li>Select 'getIndexValues' for the field 'Operation' in the WSDL gadget.</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step10.png" alt="Web service gadget after selecting getIndexvalues operation" title="Web service gadget after selecting ggetIndexValues operation"/></p><br/><br/>

<li>Click on the Text and connect as below. Note the two Text gadgets have been used. One text field here will mention the indexName, and other one will mention the indexedColum which as two parameters which is required to to the 'getIndexValues' operation.</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step11.png" alt="Web service gadget with text gadget" title="Web service gadget wih text gadget"/></p><br/><br/>

<li>Now click on 'Combo box'. It'll immediately take to the design view, there you can resize and locate the combo box where ever you like. Then switch back to the 'DataFlow' view. Connect the 'return' node from the WSDL gadget to the 'text' node of the combo box as shown below.</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step12.png" alt="Web service gadget with combo box" title="Web service gadget wih combo box"/></p><br/><br/>

<li>This states the return value from the web service method is used to fill the combo box. Now go to the design view, there you can see the unique names of the data centers. (which is returned from the web service)</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step13.png" alt="Combo box in design view" title="Combo box in design view"/></p><br/><br/>

<li>
Click on the Cassendra sources. And fill it as the following and click on load button</li>
<ul>
<li>Tablename: ClusterSummary (Where the summarizes data is stored. Refer the analyzer sequence  &lt;put&gt; tag)</li>
<li>TableIndexName: ClusterIndex (Name of the index which was created to query the ClusterSummary)</li>
<li>Index: dataCenter(Name of the field for which the index was created)</li>
</ul><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step14.png" alt="Cassendra source gadget" title="Cassendra source gadget"/></p><br/><br/>

<li>Click on the lexical string and and connect as below shown.</li>
<ul>
<li>Combo box-text &#8594; Cassendra source-from0</li>
<li>Combo box-text &#8594; lexicalString-text</li>
<li>lexicalString-text &#8594; cassendra source-to</li>
</ul><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step15.png" alt="Lexical String gadget" title="Lexical String gadget"/></p><br/><br/>

<li>Click on the bar chart. It'll take to the design view, locate the gadget as you prefer.</li><br/><br/>

<li>Switch to the Dataflow view. Connect</li>
 <ul><li>Cassendra Source-Cluster &#8594; lable-Bar Chart.</li>
<li> Cassendra Source-request count&#8594; value-Bar Chart.</li></ul><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step17.png" alt="Bar chart - Data flow" title="Bar chart - Data flow"/></p><br/><br/>

<li>Switch to design view and see the barchart. You can select the data center from the combo box and the bar chart will show the values for that data center</li>
<ul><li>Bar chart output of Grid sys data center</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step18.png" alt="Bar chart - GridSys" title="Bar chart - GridSys"/></p><br/><br/>
<li>Bar chart output of NetVest data center</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step19.png" alt="Bar chart - NetVest" title="Bar chart - NetVest"/></p></ul><br/><br/>

<li>Go to the DtaaFlow view and Click on the 'Pie chart'. Then position the pie-chart in the design view as previouse steps and switch back to the DataFlow view. Connect,</li>
<ul><li>Cassendra Source-Cluster &#8594; lable-Pie Chart.</li>
<li> Cassendra Source-fault count&#8594; value-Bar Chart.</li></ul><br/><br/> 
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step20.png" alt="Pie chart - Data Flow view" title="Pie chart - Data Flow view"/></p><br/><br/>

<li>Now switch to the Design view and see the pie chart. You can select the data center as mentioned in the above step form the combo box.</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step21.png" alt="Pie chart - Design view" title="Pie chart - Design view"/></p><br/><br/>

<li>Go to DataFlow view and Click on the table. Position the table in the design view. And rhen connect,<br/>
Table-rows &#8594; row-Cassendra Source.</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step22.png" alt="Table - Data flow" title="Table - Data flow"/></p><br/><br/>


<li>Switch to the design view and see the table. Here also you can select the data center from combo box and see the respective data center values.</li>
<ul><li>Final gadget view for NetVest data center</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step23.png" alt="NetVest - All gadgets" title="NetVest - All gadgets"/></p><br/><br/>

<li>Final gadget view for GridSys data center</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step24.png" alt="GridSys - All gadgets" title="GridSys - All gadgets"/></p><br/><br/>
</ul>

<li>Now you can see the created gadget from the main dash board.</li>
</ol>



<h2>Step 7 - Publish the gadget to dashboard</h2>
<ol>
<li>Go to the settings in gadget ide side pane and click on the publish</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step25.png" alt="Publish gadget" title="Publish gadget"/></p><br/><br/>
<li>Type a name of the gadget and click on publish. A URL will be popped out. Copy the URL. <br/>
Eg: /registry/resource/_system/config/repository/dashboards/gadgets/ClusterSummary.xml</li>

<li>Go to BAM server home page, and click on the BAM dashboard.</li>
<li>Click on the Add Gadget, and paste the URL copied which publishing the gadget.</li><br/><br/>
<p><img src="./images/cluster_monitor_step26.png" alt="Add gadget to dashboard" title="Add gadget to dashboard"/></p><br/><br/>
<li>Add click on the add gadget.</li>
</ol>

<p>Now we have come to the end of the sample and now you know the way of generating the custom gadgets from BAM and monitoring your services in clustered environment. </p>

    </body>
</document>

