<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    
    <properties>
        <title>
            Monitoring Servers
        </title>
    </properties>
    
    <head>
        <meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=iso-8859-1"/>
        <link href="css/bam-docs.css" rel="stylesheet"/>
        <link href="styles/dist-docs.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" media="all"/>
    </head>
    <body xml:lang="en">
                
        <h1>
            Monitoring Servers
        </h1>
        
        <p>
            With WSO2 BAM, you can add
            servers to be monitored. Once you add a monitored server using the management
            console, a database record will be created for that server in the WSO2 BAM database.
            This is the primary resource in the database's entity hierarchy that is
            referenced by all other data storing tables.
        </p>
        
        <h2>
            Adding a server
        </h2>
        
        <p>
            Server addition is driven by
            two types of data collection methods
        </p>
        
        <ol>
		<li>
        <h3>Polling</h3>
        <p>
		    WSO2 BAM will poll the server being monitored on a periodic basis. In the
            current implementation the polling interval is one minute and is not
            configurable.
        </p>
		</li>
		<li>
            <h3>Eventing</h3>
        <p>
		    WSO2 BAM will subscribe to the events published by the server being
            monitored. Event publication is done using WS-Eventing specification. Note that
            for this method to work, the server being added must have a publisher endpoint.
            There are three types of publishers, service data publisher for WSO2 Application Server,
            mediation data publisher for WSO2 ESB that are available as independent components that can be used to
            publish data from those respective server types. Also another type of publishers called Activity Publishers are available for
            tracing message flows. See the <a href="./data_publishers.html">documentation on data
            publishers</a> for more details on data publishers. 
        </p>
        </li>
		<li>
            <h3>Generic</h3>
        <p>
		 WSO2 BAM will neither poll nor subscribe to the server being monitored. The server can publish data to WSO2 BAM, using user defined data event 		publisher. This type of a server is useful, when it is desired to store data that does not fall into server data or mediation data categories.  
        </p>
        </li>
        </ol>
        <h3>
            Adding a server for polling data
        </h3>
        
        <p>
            <img src="./images/bam-server-add-polling.png" alt="WSO2 BAM Polling Servers" title="WSO2 BAM Polling Servers"/>
        </p>
        
        <p>
            For this you have to select
            Polling as the statistics collection method.
        </p>
        
        <p>
            WSO2 WSAS instances can be
            monitored using data polling mechanism. The versions of WSO2 WSAS supported
            with this model include 3.0.0 and upwards. 
        </p>
        
        <p>
            You can enter the server URL
            in the following format
        </p>
        
        <p>
            https://[host name]:[port]
        </p>
        
        <p>
            For example:
        </p>
        
        <p>
            https://localhost:9443
        </p>
        
        <p>
            NOTE: If you are running
            both WSO2 WSAS and WSO2 BAM on the same server, you MUST run one of the servers
            with a web context name other than root context. See the following document on
            how to <a href="https://www.wso2.org/wiki/display/carbon/same+host+as+standalone+servers+2.0">
            	set a web context with a WSO2 Carbon based servers</a>. 
        </p>
        
        <p>
            If you are running WSO2 WSAS
            with a Web context, then you have to provide the server URL with the context
            name.
        </p>
        
        <p>
            https://[host name]:[port]/[context name]
        </p>
        
        <p>
            For e.g. if wsas is the web
            context name in use
        </p>
        
        <p>
            https://localhost:9443/wsas
        </p>
        
        <p>
            When you select the data
            collection method to be polling, the type of statistics that can be collected
            is limited to Service. This is because, with polling model, in the current
            implementation of WSO2 BAM, we only support pulling data from WSO2 WSAS. In other
            words, polling mediation or message level data is not supported.
        </p>
        
        <p>
            Since the polling model uses
            the statistics administrative service on WSO2 WSAS server, a user name and
            password with administrative privileges on the WSO2 WSAS server instance is
            also required to add a server to be polled.
        </p>
        
        <p>
            You can also provide a
            description of the server being added, which could be useful in your future
            references to the monitored server.
        </p>
        
        <h3>
            Adding a server for
            subscribing for events
        </h3>
        
        <p>
            <img src="./images/bam-server-add-eventing.png" alt="WSO2 BAM Eventing Servers" title="WSO2 BAM Eventing Servers"/>
        </p>
        
        <p>
            For this, you have to select
            <b>Eventing</b> as the statistics collection method. Like in the case of polling, you
            can provide the server URL using the format
        </p>
        
        <p>
            <b>https://[host
            name]:[port]&lt;/[web context name]&gt;</b>
             
        </p>
        
        
        <p>
            Also, note that, if you have
            set the host name setting in the carbon.xml file of the server being added, you
            must use that host name, and not the server IP, when adding the server as
            server URL. If you have not set host name setting in carbon.xml file of the
            server being added, then you must use the IP address of the server being added,
            in place of the host name. To make sure that you can keep on monitoring the
            server irrespective of IP changes, due to relocation of a server instance that
            is being monitored with WSO2 BAM, it is advised that you use the host name
            setting and use the host name instead of the IP when adding the server to be
            monitored with WSO2 BAM.
        </p>
        
        
        <p>
            The eventing model supports
            Service data and Mediation data.
        </p>
        
        <p>
            Service data can be
            collected from service data publishers deployed with WSO2 WSAS instances.Here,you have to select
            <b>Eventing</b> as the statistics collection method and Type of Data as <b>Service.</b> ServerURL 
            you need to provide as explained above.<br/>
            eg:<i>https://10.100.1.143:9443/wsas</i>
        </p>
        
        <p>
            Mediation data can be collected from mediation data publishers deployed 
            with WSO2 ESB instances.Here,you have to select
            <b>Eventing</b> as the statistics collection method and Type of Data as <b>Mediation.</b> ServerURL 
            you need to provide as explained above.<br/>
            eg:<i>https://10.100.1.143:9443/esb</i>
        </p>

        <p>
            Activity data can be collected from activity data publishers deployed 
            with WSO2 ESB, WSO2 Application Server or WSO2 Data Service Server instances.Here,you have to select
            <b>Eventing</b> as the statistics collection method and Type of Data as <b>Message.</b> ServerURL 
            you need to provide as explained above.<br/>
            eg:<i>https://10.100.1.143:9443/esb</i>
        </p>
        
        <p>
            The corresponding event
            message subscribing endpoints are built into WSO2 BAM and will work out of the
            box. However, you have to ensure that the data publishers are deployed with the
            server being added so that they can publish the data using WS-Eventing. Data
            publishers are shipped as separate components, and you can find more information
            on how to install them in <a href="./data_publishers.html">data publishers documentation</a>. 
        </p>
        
        <p>
            You can also provide a
            description of the server being added, which could be useful in your future
            references to the monitored server.
        </p>
        
        <h3>
            Adding a generic server
        </h3>
        <p>
            <img src="./images/bam-server-add-generic.png" alt="WSO2 BAM Generic Servers" title="WSO2 BAM Generic Servers"/>
        </p>
        
        <p>
            For this, you have to select
            Generic as the data collection method. Once you select Generic, you will have
            to provide only the server URL and server description. The URL will not be
            validated for this case. When you are publishing data to WSO2 BAM against a Generic
            server, all you have to do is to use the server URL given as the data source.
            See documentation on <a href="./data_publishers.html">data publishers</a> for more information. 
        </p>
        
        <h2>
            List Monitored Servers
        </h2>
        
		<p>
            <img src="./images/bam-monitored-servers.png" alt="WSO2 BAM Generic Servers" title="WSO2 BAM Generic Servers"/>
        </p>
		
        <p>
            The monitored server details
            page list the server URL, stat collection method, stat type, active/inactive
            status and the description for each server. Based on the current server status,
            you will be able to either activate or deactivate a monitored server. In the
            active state, data for the server would be collected, using the corresponding
            stat collection method, and in the inactive state, no current data would be
            collected. Note that, in the current implementation of WSO2 BAM, it is not
            allowed to delete a server, from the management console. This was done purposely,
            to guard against deleting valuable historical data, collected over time, for a
            server. Note that, with BAM, even though a server might not be used any more,
            the data collected against that server would be useful with analytics. Hence,
            rather than deleting, you can retire a server by deactivating it. Even if you
            happen to use a given server for a different set of services, over time, it is
            perfectly fine to use the same server instance in WSO2 BAM, as it captures data
            along with time dimension.
        </p>
        
        <p>
            If it is absolutely
            necessary to delete a server instance, then it is advised that you do this at
            the database layer directly. 
        </p>
    </body>
</document>

