<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    
    <properties>
        <title>
            Visualization
        </title>
    </properties>
    <head>
        <meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=iso-8859-1"/>
        <link href="css/bam-docs.css" rel="stylesheet"/>
        <link href="styles/dist-docs.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" media="all"/>
    </head>
    <body xml:lang="en">
        
        <h1>
            Visualization
        </h1>
        
        <p>
            WSO2 BAM provides users with
            visualization tools to help discover information and knowledge. Once the users
            discover information, the results can be used for decision support. However,
            for the right decisions to be made, information discovery needs to happen
            first.
        </p>
        
        <p>
            Visual tools can condense
            thousands of numbers into one picture. That makes the information more
            attractive and understandable to users.
        </p>
        
        <p>
            Among the visualization
            tools that come with WSO2 BAM are the dashboards and visual analysis tools.
            There is also support for generating reports.
        </p>
        
        <h2>
            Dashboards
        </h2>
        
        <p>
            Dashboards provide visual
            displays of important information consolidated and arranged on a single screen,
            hence information can be digested in a single glance and easily explored. There
            are multiple dashboards that ship with WSO2 BAM:
        </p>
        
        <ul>
            <li>
                Main dashboard
            </li>
            <li>
                Service data dashboard
            </li>
            <li>
                Mediation data dashboard
            </li>
            <li>
                Service analytics dashboard
            </li>
            <li>
                Mediation analytics dashboard
            </li>
        </ul>
        
        <p>
            The main dashboard consists
            of Gadgets [TODO: link to gadget server]. The set of predefined gadgets that
            ship with WSO2 BAM help users to visualize the trends depicted by the monitored
            server data. These gadgets are organized into multiple tabs, to help users classify
            and segment selected chunks of information. Users can rearrange the default arrangement,
            in sync with their monitoring aspirations. Moreover users can define their own
            gadgets to be included in the dashboard. [TODO: link to how to write a gadget]
            Hence the main dashboard is highly customizable.
        </p>
        
        <p>
            WSO2 BAM has support for operational,
            tactical and strategic dashboards.
        </p>
        
        <p>
            Operational dashboards are
            to be used by front line workers and supervisors to monitor key operational
            data that are lightly summarized and updated as and when the latest data is
            available. For example, latest counts and time measures for both service and
            mediation data are available as operational dashboards.
        </p>
        
        <p>
            Tactical dashboards are to
            be used by managers and analysts on data that are summarized over hourly, daily
            and monthly basis.
        </p>
        
        <p>
            Strategic dashboards can be
            used by executives and managers on data that are summarized on monthly or
            quarterly basis, to monitor the execution of strategic objectives.
        </p>
        
        <p>
            Service data and mediation
            data dashboards are operational level dashboards. Tactical and strategic
            aspects of dashboards are embedded in the service and mediation analytics
            dashboards.
        </p>
        
        <h3>
            Analytics
        </h3>
        
        <p>
            Analytical decision making
            is a strategic weapon for companies. Analytics is the science of analysis. WSO2
            BAM provides means to analyze the service and mediation data, summarized over
            time dimensions. Users can dig into information on the request, response, and
            fault counts as well as average time information for various levels of service
            invocations and mediation data, to help identify trends in the usage of
            services and message mediation patterns. These information can be used to help
            with strategic decision making in both IT and business domains. For example, IT
            can make use of analytics to help with capacity planning for the SOA
            infrastructure. Business decision makers can monitor the business trends and
            decide on what business functions to expand, and what steps to be taken to
            increase the percentage of successfully closed deals. In other words, business
            users can fine tune the business processes, based on the knowledge discovered.
        </p>
        
        <p>
            The knowledge discovery
            facilitated by the visualization tools of WSO2 BAM help identify valid, novel,
            potentially useful and ultimately understandable patterns in data that are
            being collected.
        </p>
        
        <p>
            The summarizations in the analytics dashboards are based on time dimensions.
            Both service data and mediation data are summarized into the following time
            dimensions:
        </p>
        
        <ul>
            <li>
                Hour
            </li>
            <li>
                Day
            </li>
            <li>
                Month
            </li>
            <li>
                Quarter
            </li>
            <li>
                Year
            </li>
        </ul>
        
        <p>
            Based on the above time dimensions, WSO2 BAM summarizes the collected data
            in the following manner.
        </p>
        
        <ul>
            <li>
                At the top of each hour, the
                data for the last hour will be summarized
            </li>
            <li>
                At midnight, the data for the
                previous day would be summarized
            </li>
            <li>
                At midnight of the last day
                of each month, the data for the previous day would be summarized
            </li>
            <li>
                At midnight of the last day
                of each quarter, the data for the previous quarter would be summarized.
                The four quarters are January to March, April to June, July to September
                and October to December
            </li>
            <li>
                At midnight of the 31
                <sup>
                    st
                </sup>
                of December, the data for the previous year would be summarized
            </li>
        </ul>
    </body>
</document>
