<!--
  ~ Copyright 2005-2007 WSO2, Inc. (http://wso2.com)
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN"
        "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">

<html>
    <body>
        <p>[
            <a
                    href="http://wso2.org/downloads/appserver">Download
            </a>
            ]
            | [
            <a href="../index_docs.html">Documentation Home</a>
            ] | [
            <a
                    href="../release_notes.html">Release Notes
            </a>
            ]
        </p>
        <h1>MAR Validator</h1>

        <p>The aim of this document is to explain briefly how the Module Validator (MAR Validator)
            tool works.
        </p>

        <h2>Content</h2>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <a href="#intro">Introduction</a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="#usage">Usage</a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="#conclusion">Conclusion</a>
            </li>
        </ul>
        <a id="intro"></a>

        <h2>Introduction</h2>

        <p></p>
        MAR Validator is a graphical tool available with WSO2 Application Server that
        allows the user to validate a Web Services Module (known as a MAR file, due to the .mar extension).

        <a id="usage"></a>
        <h2>Usage</h2>

        <p>Validating a module before is deployed can come quite handy,
            because it will provide an assurance of the validity of the module in question.
            Using MAR Validator is quite easy, and as with the other tools
            provided on the WSO2 Application Server front page,
            you don't even need to sign in.
        </p>

        <p>Click on
            <strong>MAR Validator</strong>
            and you will be taken to the following screen.
        </p>

        <p>
            <img alt="Figure: MAR Validator Screen 1" src="../images/tools/mar_val_1.jpg"/>
        </p>

        <p>
            There are two different ways in which we can provide the tool with the module which needs
            to be validated. We can either provide a module archive (a .mar file) or a module descriptor
            (a module.xml file).
        </p>

        <p>First lets consider the scenario of validating a module archive (MAR file).</p>
        <p>click on the
        <strong>Browse</strong>
            on the "Select a MAR" box to search your file system for
            the .mar file which represents the module archive you want to validate. Once
            you have selected it, click on the <strong>Validate MAR</strong> button to validate the module.xml inside it.
        </p>
        <strong>Note: In case of a MAR Validation what actually happens is that the module.xml file inside the
            archive is extracted and validated.
        </strong>

        <p>Next, lets consider the other option, namely, directly pointing to a module.xml file to validate.</p>
        <p>Click on the
        <strong>Browse</strong> button in the "Select a module.xml" box to search your file system for
            the module.xml file which you want to validate. Once you have selected it, click on
            "Validate
            Module.xml"
            button to validate the module descriptor.
        </p>

        <p>
            <img alt="Figure: MAR Validator Results Screen" src="../images/tools/mar_val_2.jpg"/>
        </p>

        <p>In both of the above methods, when the validation process has completed,
            you will be taken to the results page.
            This page will display the validation results in tabular form.
        </p>

        <p>If we take a closer look at the inner workings of the validation process, in
            module.xml validation,
            the tool parses the input module.xml against a schema and looks for any invalidities.
            If any are found, they are presented in a tabular form.
        </p>


        <a id="conclusion"></a>
        <h2>Conclusion</h2>

        <p>MAR validation provides a handy method of validating a MAR archive or a module.xml file
            and viewing the results in a
            tabular form.
        </p>

        <br/>

    </body>
</html>
