<!--
  ~ Copyright 2005-2007 WSO2, Inc. (http://wso2.com)
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN"
        "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<body>
<p>[<a
        href="http://wso2.org/downloads/appserver">Download</a>]
    | [<a href="../index_docs.html">Documentation Home</a>] | [<a
        href="../release_notes.html">Release Note</a>]</p>

<h1>Try It - Invoke a Remote Web Service</h1>

<p>The aim of this document is to explain briefly how the Try It tool works. </p>

<h2>Content</h2>
<ul>
    <li><a href="#intro">Introduction</a></li>
    <li><a href="#usage">Usage</a></li>
    <li><a href="#conclusion">Conclusion</a></li>
</ul>
<a id="intro"></a>

<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p>Try It is a handy tool available with WSO2 Application Server that
    allows the user to try out your own WSDL (Web Services Definition Language) or
    any publicly available WSDL of the document/literal style .</p>

    <a id="usage"></a>

<h2>Usage</h2>

<p>Using Try It is quite straightforward. In fact, as with the other tools
    provided on the WSO2 Application Server front page, you don't even need to
    sign in. </p>

<p>Click on <strong>Try It</strong> and you will be taken to the following screen.</p>

<p><img alt="Figure:Try It Screen 1" src="../images/tools/tryit_1.jpg"/></p>

<p>Here, in the provided field, either type in or paste the location of a WSDL.
    It may be a local file system path, or a web URL. You can invoke practically any WSDL
    from anywhere in the world, with the condition that it uses the document/literal (doc/lit)
    style.</p>

<p>Once you've enetered the WSDL path or location, click on Try It. If yopur browser has Popup-Blocking
    enabled, you may receive a message saying a popup was blocked. If this occurs, choose to allow popups for
    the current domain and try again.</p>

<p>
    You should be presented with a screen that lists the available operations in the gioven WSDL.
    Here, for operations that take arguments, you will see fields that allow you to set values
    for the primitive argumant types that will be passed to the operations. For no-argument operations
    you will just see the button which has the same name as the operation.</p>
<img alt="Figure:Try It Screen 2" src="../images/tools/tryit_2.jpg"/>
<p>In either case, clicking on the button will invoke that service operation and in a few seconds,
    you will be able to see the return value immediately next to the button.</p>

<p><img alt="Figure:Try It Response Screen" src="../images/tools/tryit_3.jpg"/></p>

<a id="conclusion"></a>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Try It provides you with a mechanism to test your WSDL by creating end points on-the-fly.
    It can come quite handy in sounding out a WSDL before actually coding for it, without the need to
go to a third party WSDL validator tool.</p>

<br/>

</body>
</html>
