<!--
  ~ Copyright 2005-2007 WSO2, Inc. (http://wso2.com)
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN"
        "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html>
    <body>
        <p>[
            <a
                    href="http://wso2.org/downloads/appserver">Download
            </a>
            ]
            | [
            <a href="../index_docs.html">Documentation Home</a>
            ] | [
            <a
                    href="../release_notes.html">Release Notes
            </a>
            ]
        </p>
        <h1>WSDL Converter - Convert WSDL 1.1 Documents to WSDL 2.0 Documents</h1>

        <p>The aim of this document is to explain briefly how the WSDL Converter tool works.</p>

        <h2>Content</h2>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <a href="#intro">Introduction</a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="#usage">Usage</a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="#conclusion">Conclusion</a>
            </li>
        </ul>
        <a id="intro"></a>

        <h2>Introduction</h2>

        <p>
            WSDL Converter is a tool available with WSO2 Application Server that
            allows the user to generate a WSDL version 2.0 document from a WSDL version 1.1
            document.
        </p>

        <a id="usage"></a>
        <h2>Usage</h2>

        <p>
            Given a WSDL 1.1 document, the ability to generate a WSDL 2.0 document can be very useful.
            Currently 1.1 version is the widely used version of WSDL, but recently WSDL 2.0 has been gaining
            popularity. So WSDL Converter provides an easy path to users who may be looking to make the switch
            to WSDL 2.0 from 1.1.</p>
        <p>Using WSDL Converter is quite easy, and as with
            the other tools provided on the WSO2 Application Server front page,
            you don't even need to sign in.
        </p>

        <p>Click on <strong>WSDL Converter</strong>
            and you will be taken to the following screen.
        </p>

        <p>
            <img alt="Figure:WSDL Converter Selection Screen" src="../images/tools/wsdlconverter_1.jpg"/>
        </p>

        <p>There are two different ways of providing input to the WSDL Converter.
            You can either upload a WSDL 1.1 document existing in your local file system, or you can
            directly enter the URL of a WSDL 1.1 document that resides on the web.
        </p>

        <p>First lets consider the scenario of uploading a WSDL vsersion 1.1 document.
        Click on the
        <strong>Browse</strong> button in the "Upload your WSDL 1.1" box to search your file system for
            the WSDL 1.1 file, i.e. the document which represent the Web Service, you want to convert to a
            version 2.0 document. Once you have selected it, click on "Convert WSDL 1.1 -> 2.0"
            button to begin the conversion.
        </p>

        <p>
            Next, lets consider the other scenario of directly pointing to a URL that holds the WSDL 1.1
            document. In the "Type WSDL 1.1 document URL" box, type in or paste a valid WSDL 1.1 document URL.
            Then click on "Convert WSDL 1.1 -> 2.0" button to convert it
            to its corresponding WSDL 2.0 document.
        </p>
        <strong>Note: In the second scenario, the WSDL 1.1 document resource will be
            downloaded to a tempory location on the server's file system and then the conversion will happen.
        </strong>

          <p>After following either of the scenarios, you will be taken to
            the Results page. </p>
		<p>
            <img alt="Figure:WSDL Converter Result Screen" src="../images/tools/wsdlconverter_2.jpg"/>
        </p>
		<p>This page will display the converted WSDL 2.0 document, given the process
            happened smoothly without any errors which should be the case for any valid and correct WSDL 1.1 document.
            You can save the given page on your local file system.
        </p>

        <p>Taking a look at the inside workings of the conversion process, the following steps
            occur prior to producing the result document.
            First the WSDL 1.1 document will be parsed to extract the details. Note that no validation of
            the WSDL against a schema here. After the data is extracted, with it, the WSDL 2.0
            document will be generated employing a template with XSL Transformation. While this is happening,
            any invalid alterations and/or anomalies will be picked up, and if they exist, the conversion process will be aborted.
        </p>


        <a id="conclusion"></a>
        <h2>Conclusion</h2>

        <p>WSDL Converter provides an easy method to generate WSDL version 2.0 document from an existing WSDL 1.1 document.
        </p>

        <br/>

    </body>
</html>
