<!--
  ~ Copyright 2005-2007 WSO2, Inc. (http://wso2.com)
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN"
        "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <body>
        <p>[
            <a
                    href="http://wso2.org/downloads/appserver">Download
            </a>
            ]
            | [
            <a href="../index_docs.html">Documentation Home</a>
            ] | [
            <a
                    href="../release_notes.html">Release Note
            </a>
            ]
        </p>
        <h1>WSDLView - Generate the WSDL Document Starting with a Java Class</h1>

        <p>The aim of this document is to explain briefly how the WSDLView tool works.</p>

        <h2>Content</h2>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <a href="#intro">Introduction</a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="#usage">Usage</a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="#conclusion">Conclusion</a>
            </li>
        </ul>
        <a id="intro"></a>

        <h2>Introduction</h2>

        <p></p>
        WSDLView is a handy tool available with WSO2 Application Server that
        allows the user to generate a WSDL (Web Services Definition Language)
        document from any given .class or .jar file(s).

        <a id="usage"></a>
        <h2>Usage</h2>

        <p>Using WSDLView is quite straightforward. In fact, as with the other tools
            provided on the WSO2 Application Server front page, you don't even need to
            sign in.
        </p>

        <p>Click on
            <strong>WSDL View</strong>
            and you will be taken to the following screen.
        </p>

        <p>
            <img alt="Figure:WSDL View Class Selection Screen" src="../images/tools/wsdlview_1.jpg"/>
        </p>

        <p>Here, click on
            <strong>Browse</strong>
            to search your file system for
            the .class file or the .jar file you want to generate a WSDL for. Once
            you have selected it, use the
            <strong>+</strong>
            button to add other necessary
            classes or jars.
        </p>
        <strong>Note: In case of a .class file, it needs to be declared in the
            default package for WSDLView to work. If you need to WSDLView for a
            class inside a custom package, please jar up the class files first.
        </strong>

         <p>Once you've selected all necessary resources, click on
            <strong>Next</strong>
            to move on to the WSDLView configuration screen.
        </p>

        <p>
            <img alt="Figure:WSDL View Options Screen" src="../images/tools/wsdlview_2.jpg"/>

        </p>

        <p>On this screen, you can customize the WSDL generation process to your liking.
            The description given against each configuration option should give you
            an idea of what it does. Some of the more importants options are described below.
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <strong>cn</strong>
                : The main class for which the WSDL should be generated. Note that it
                should be fully qualified with the package name.
            </li>
            <li><strong>sn</strong>: The name of the service</li>
        </ul>

        For the options that you leave unchanged, the default values will be used
        in the generation process. Click on
        <strong>Generate</strong>
        .

        <p>If everything is in order, the generation should happen smoothly and produce the WSDL.</p>
		<img alt="Figure:WSDL View WSDL Screen" src="../images/tools/wsdlview_3.jpg"/>

          <p>  In case you are taken to the "Add Resources" screen with a "
            class not found"
            message, it could mean that you specified an incorrect classname in the previous screen, or you did not
            include a necessary resource file, or as mentioned above you selected a .class that was
            declared in a package other than the default package. If that happens,
            rectify the error and click "Generate" again.
        </p>


        <a id="conclusion"></a>
        <h2>Conclusion</h2>

        <p>WSDLView provides an easy to configure and easy to use method of producing a WSDL document from
            already existing classes.
        </p>

        <br/>

    </body>
</html>
