<!--
  ~ Copyright 2005-2007 WSO2, Inc. (http://wso2.com)
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN"
        "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">

<html>
    <body>
<p>[<a
href="http://dist.wso2.org/products/appserver/java/5.0.2">Download</a>]
| [<a href="index_docs.html">Documentation Index</a>] | [<a
href="release_notes.html">Release Note</a>]</p>
        <h1>Data Services Guide</h1>

        <p>WSO2 Data Services feature provides a convenient Web service interface for data
            stored in sources such as relational databases, CSV files and MS-Excel files. With
            WSO2 Data Services, data can be exposed and accessed in a secure (using WS-Security)
            and reliable (using WS-ReliableMessaging) manner; data is also made available for
            mashing-up with other Web services.</p>

        <p>WSO2 Data Services is shipped as a separate product as well. You can download it from
            <a href="http://wso2.org/downloads/dss">here</a>. It is also added into WSO2
            Application Server as it is more easy to manage all kinds of Web Services (Axis2, JAX-WS,
            Data Services etc) in a single server. And also it's a common use case in production
            systems to run Axis2 services together with Data services.</p>

        <p>In WSO2 Carbon platform, there are Data Services related features which can be installed
            into any of our Carbon based product. Therefore, in both WSO2 AS and WSO2 DSS, same set
            of Data Services features are used. So you can select the best option depending on
            your requirement.</p>

        <p>For a quick introduction to WSO2 Data services, you can follow the guide
            <a href="ds/docs/userguide.html">here</a>. If you need a comprehensive guide, please
            download the WSO2 Data Services Server documentation from
            <a href="http://wso2.org/downloads/dss">here</a>.</p>

        <p>You can find more useful articles and tutorials on Data Services from
            <a href="http://wso2.org/library/dss">here</a> as well.</p>

    </body>
</html>
