<!--
  ~ Copyright 2005-2007 WSO2, Inc. (http://wso2.com)
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN"
       "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<body>
<h1>
    Welcome to WSO2 Application Server (WSO2 AppServer)
</h1>

<p>[<a
href="http://wso2.org/downloads/appserver">Download</a>]
| [<a href="index_docs.html">Documentation Home</a>] | [<a
href="release_notes.html">Release Note</a>]</p>

<p>WSO2 AppServer is an enterprise-ready application server based on the WSO2 Carbon
    platform. Being the successor of the WSO2 Web Services Application Server (WSAS),
    WSO2 Application Server (AS) supports web application deployment and management
    in addition to its web services management capabilities. Coupled with WSO2 Carbon
    features, users now have the capability to manage their applications that range
    from Web Services to web applications in a unified manner within the AppServer
    management console itself.</p>

<p>Based on the concept of Service Oriented Architecture (SOA), the Web services
    specifications support secure, reliable and transactional integration based
    on the concept of loose coupling, which is inherently scalable. Many vendors
    have "bolted on" support for Web services and XML to their existing proprietary
    product solutions. WSO2 has created a new platform that cuts out unnecessary
    layers, supporting the full WS-* stack in a simple, clean, lightweight model,
    making it easier to develop, deploy and run applications.</p>

<p>When it comes to supporting web applications, WSO2 AppServer internally utilizing
    Apache Tomcat and capable of hosting any kind of web application which is deployable
    on Tomcat. In addition to that, these web applications can inherit features like
    Authentication/Authorization, User management etc. from the WSO2 Carbon platform.</p>

<p>WSO2 AppServer comes with full support for XML, SOAP, WSDL, and supports reliable,
    secure communications. WSO2 AppServer makes it simple and effective
    to create, consume and manage Web services.</p>

<h3>WS-* Support</h3>
<ul>
  <li>SOAP 1.1/1.2</li>
  <li>WSDL 1.1</li>
  <li>WSDL 2.0</li>
  <li>JAX-WS 2.2</li>
  <li>MTOM, XOP &amp; SOAP with Attachments</li>
  <li>WS-Addressing</li>
  <li>WS-Security</li>
  <li>WS-Trust</li>
  <li>WS-SecureConversation</li>
  <li>WS-MetaDataExchange</li>
  <li>WS-SecurityPolicy</li>
  <li>WS-ReliableMessaging</li>
  <li>WS-Policy</li>
  <li>WS-PolicyAttachment</li>
  <li>WS-MetadataExchange</li>
  <li>WS-Transfer</li>
  <li>WS-Discovery</li>
</ul>

<p>WSO2 AppServer brings together a number of open source projects into a single,
    seamless, easy-to-use offering. Instead of having to download the different
    parts of the Apache Web services stack separately and assemble them together,
    we have done that for you and offer you a single integrated package with lot
    of additional features which are inherited from the WSO2 Carbon platform.
</p>

<h3>Open Source Components of WSO2 AppServer</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Apache Axis2 (SOAP)</li>
  <li>Apache Axiom (High performance XML Object Model)</li>
  <li>Apache Rampart/Apache WSS4J (WS-Security, WS-SecureConversation)</li>
  <li>Apache Rahas (WS-Trust)</li>
  <li>Apache Sandesha2 (WS-ReliableMessaging)</li>
  <li>WS-Addressing implementation in Axis2</li>
  <li>Apache Neethi (WS-Policy)</li>
  <li>WS-SecurityPolicy implementation in Axis2</li>
  <li>Apache XML Schema</li>
  <li>Embedded Apache Tomcat</li>
  <li>Apache Tribes (Group Communications Framework)</li>
</ul>

<h3>WSO2 AppServer can be used in a number of different scenarios:</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Exposing existing or new business applications as Web services.</li>
  <li>Building reliable messaging links within or across enterprises.</li>
  <li>Hosting applications as WebApps</li>
  <li>Integrating with .NET, J2EE, CICS, SAP and other platforms.</li>
</ul>

<p>WSO2 AppServer is a fully open source product. WSO2 contributes to the Apache
    Software Foundation's Web services project through a combination of leading
    open source components. Together with our own integration code, WSO2 offers
    production quality open source software. All our integration code including
    the unified management console is available under the Apache
    Software License version 2.0.</p>

<h2>New Features In This Release</h2>
<ul>
        <li>Inbuilt Data Services support</li>
        <li>Server Roles Management feature</li>
        <li>Improved JAX-WS Support</li>
        <li>Improved SOAP Tracer</li>
        <li>Improvements in Service listing page
            <ul>
                <li>Two lists for Services and Service Groups</li>
                <li>Security Indicators within service list</li>
            </ul>
        </li>
        <li>Improved Samples and documentation</li>
        <li>Improved Class loading for Web apps and Web Services</li>
        <li>Embedded Tomcat 7.0.14 support</li>
        <li>Servlet API 3.0 support</li>
    </ul>

<p>
    The complete list of features is available in the
    <a href="release_notes.html">Release Note</a>.
</p>

<h2>WSO2 Application Server Documentation</h2>

<p>
    See the <a href="index_docs.html">full list of documents</a>
    with instructions on installation, administration, sample guides and how
    to use the tools packaged with WSO2 AppServer.
</p>

<h2>Mailing Lists</h2>

<p>Your feedback on WSO2 AppServer is most appreciated. Please send them to our
user mailing lists:</p>
<ul>
  <li>WSO2 AppServer Users' mailing list: <a
    href="mailto:wsas-java-user@wso2.org">appserver user list</a> | <a
    href="mailto:wsas-java-user-request@wso2.org?subject=subscribe">Subscribe</a>
    | <a
    href="mailto:wsas-java-user-request@wso2.org?subject=unsubscribe">Unsubscribe</a>
    | <a href="http://wso2.org/mailarchive/wsas-java-user/">Mail
    Archive</a></li>
</ul>
<ul>
  <li>WSO2 Carbon Developers' mailing list: <a
    href="mailto:carbon-dev@wso2.org">carbon developer list</a> | <a
    href="mailto:carbon-dev-request@wso2.org?subject=subscribe">Subscribe</a>
    | <a
    href="mailto:carbon-dev-request@wso2.org?subject=unsubscribe">Unsubscribe</a>
    | <a href="http://wso2.org/mailarchive/carbon-dev/">Mail
    Archive</a></li>
</ul>
<ul>
    <li>For more information about mailing lists, please refer
        <a href="http://wso2.org/mail">http://wso2.org/mail</a>.</li>
</ul>

</body>
</html>
