<!--
  ~ Copyright 2005-2007 WSO2, Inc. (http://wso2.com)
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN"
       "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<body>
<p>[<a
href="http://wso2.org/downloads/appserver">Download</a>]
| [<a href="index_docs.html">Documentation Home</a>] | [<a
href="release_notes.html">Release Note</a>]</p>
<h1>Source Distribution</h1>

<p>This page explains how to build the WSO2 AppServer using the source
    distribution of the release. First download the AppServer source
    distribution from <a href="http://wso2.org/downloads/appserver">here</a>.</p>

<h2>System Requirements</h2>

<table border="2">
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Java Runtime Environment</td>
      <td>1.6.x (For instructions on setting up the JRE in different
        operating systems, visit <a href="http://java.sun.com">http://java.sun.com</a>)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Maven</td>
      <td>2.2.0 or higher (<a href="http://maven.apache.org/">download</a>).</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Operating System</td>
      <td>Tested on Windows XP, Windows Vista, Linux (Fedora core, Ubuntu and Gentoo),
          Mac OS X &amp; Sun Solaris</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2>Setting Up the Environment and Tools</h2>

<h3>Maven:</h3>

<p>The WSO2 AppServer build is based on <a
href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven</a>. Hence, a prerequisite to
build WSO2 AppServer from the source distribution is to have Maven and JDK
installed. Extensive instructions are available on the Maven site.</p>
    <p>
        You may need to set the MAVEN_OPTS if you come across OutOfMemory errors during
        the build. e.g. you may need to set MAVEN_OPTS=-Xmx1024m -XX:MaxPermSize=128m
    </p>

<p>This guide however contains the easiest path for quick environment
setting. Advanced users can <a
href="http://maven.apache.org/what-is-maven.html">learn more about
Maven</a>.</p>

<ul>
    <li>MS Windows
        <ul>
            <li>Download and run the Windows installer package</li>
            <li>Set the 'Environment Variables' (create the system variable M2_HOME and
                edit the path. e.g., "set M2_HOME=C:\Program Files\Apache Software
                Foundation\maven-2.0.x"; set path=%path%;%M2_HOME%\bin)</li>
            <li>Make sure that the system variable <a
                    href="setting_java_home.html">JAVA_HOME</a> is set to the location of
                your JDK, e.g., C:\Program Files\Java\jdk1.5.0_02</li>
            <li>Run 'mvn --version' to verify that it is correctly installed.</li>
        </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Unix based OS (Linux etc)
        <ul>
            <li>Download maven tar ball or the zip archive</li>
            <li>Extract it to a directory of choice</li>
            <li>Set the environment variable M2_HOME and add M2_HOME/bin to the path as well</li>
            <li>You can also refer to more instructions on <a href="http://maven.apache.org/download.html">how
                to install Maven in Unix</a> based operating systems.</li>
        </ul>
    </li>
</ul>

    <p>Once Maven is properly installed, you can start building the WSO2 AppServer for
        Java.</p>

    <h2>Building WSO2 AppServer from the Source Distribution</h2>

    <p>The <a href="http://wso2.org/downloads/appserver">source distribution</a>
        is available as a zipped archive. All the necessary build
        scripts are included with the source distribution. Expand the source archive
        to a directory of your choice. You can run the following commands inside that
        directory to build the WSO2 AppServer.<br/></p>

    <p><strong>Note:</strong> The first time you run Maven, it will automatically
        download the dependent .jars. Therefore, the first run will take more
        time. The third party libraries required by WSO2 AppServer will be downloaded from the
        Maven2 repositories specified in the main pom.xml file.<br/></p>

    <p>The list of commands that can be run are as follows. Please note that the released source
        distribution contains sources for all the WSO2 Carbon based products. Therefore if you only
        want to build the WSO2 AppServer, you have to always use the option "-Dproduct=wsas".<br/></p>

    <table border="1">
        <tbody>
            <tr>
                <td><strong>mvn clean install -Dproduct=wsas</strong></td>
                <td>To create the complete release artifacts of WSO2 AppServer including the
                    binary and source distributions.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><strong>mvn clean install -Dmaven.test.skip=true -Dproduct=wsas</strong></td>
                <td>To create the complete release artifacts of WSO2 AppServer including the binary and
                    source distributions, without running any of the unit tests.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><strong>mvn clean install -Dmaven.test.skip=true -Dproduct=wsas -o</strong></td>
                <td>To create the complete release artifacts of WSO2 AppServer including the binary and
                    source distributions, without running any of the unit tests, in offline mode. This
                    can be done only if you've already built the source at least once.</td>
            </tr>
        </tbody>
    </table>

    <p><br/></p>
    <p>All the sources of the major 3rd party components included in WSO2 AppServer can be found in
        the source distribution. For the purpose of debugging applications, you could attach these sources.</p>

</body>
</html>
